<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration or manifest of the high and mighty lords the States Generall of the Vnited Netherland Provinces: comprehending a true relation of their sincere intention, and lawfull proceedings in the treaty with the extraordinary embassadors, and the commissionaries of the present goverment [sic] of England, so as the same hath been held here in the Hague, as also at London. And likewise of the unjust and violent proceedings of those of the said government, which have forced the said States Generall by way of retortion, to defend their state and subjects against their oppressions.</title>
            <title>Declaratie ofte manifest. 1652-08-02. English.</title>
            <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89905</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N480</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E674_22</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203042</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863136</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863136</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115319</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89905)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115319)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 103:E674[22])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration or manifest of the high and mighty lords the States Generall of the Vnited Netherland Provinces: comprehending a true relation of their sincere intention, and lawfull proceedings in the treaty with the extraordinary embassadors, and the commissionaries of the present goverment [sic] of England, so as the same hath been held here in the Hague, as also at London. And likewise of the unjust and violent proceedings of those of the said government, which have forced the said States Generall by way of retortion, to defend their state and subjects against their oppressions.</title>
                  <title>Declaratie ofte manifest. 1652-08-02. English.</title>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Translated out of the originall copy, printed in the Hague by the widdow and heires of Hillebrandt Jacobsz van Wouw,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated at end: the second of August sixteen hundreth and two and fifty.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "7ber [i.e. September] 1st".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anglo-Dutch War, 1652-1654 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115319:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION OR MANIFEST OF The High and Mighty Lords THE <hi>STATES GENERALL</hi> OF THE <hi>United Netherland Provinces:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Comprehending A true Relation of their ſincere intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and lawfull proceedings in the Treaty with the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Embaſſadors, and the Commiſſionaries of the preſent Goverment of <hi>England,</hi> ſo as the ſame hath been held here in the <hi>Hague,</hi> as alſo at <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And likewiſe Of the unjuſt and violent proceedings of thoſe of the ſaid Government, which have forced the ſaid States Generall by way of retortion, to defend their State and Subjects againſt their Oppreſſions.</p>
            <p>At AMSTERDAM, Tranſlated out of the Originall Copy, Printed in the <hi>Hague</hi> by the Widdow and Heires of <hi>Hillebrandt Jacobſz van Wouw.</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115319:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115319:2"/>
            <p>THe States Generall of the United Netherlands unto all, which may ſee or hear this read, ſend greeting. Whereas all lawfull Magiſtrates (as being ordained by God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to take care of the welfare of their ſubjects) are bound, not only to govern the ſame with diſcretion, and to maintain them in good order and lawfull policy; and further, wiſely and prudently to prevent and ſuppreſſe all outward occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, whereby the reſt and tranquility of their ſaid ſubjects might be diſturbed, or they undergo loſſes or oppreſſion: and to that end it be eſteemed both honourable and profitable with good and due offices to have all, eſpecially their Neighbouring States and Countries obligued to them, whereby they may retain a wel-grounded and aſſured confidence of each others fidelity, and when any diſtemper is befalne, may with the moſt eaſie and peaceable means compoſe the ſame in all love and friendſhip. But moreover it be required of them, when the cauſe is ſo exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and no other means can prevail, to uſe the power and ſtrength given them of God Almighty, and conſequently their weapons, and therewith manly and couragiouſly to oppoſe and ſuppreſſe all violence and injury done to their ſaid dear ſubjects, and cauſe them to obtain ſatisfaction and repairation for all wrongs and damages which unjuſtly were inflicted upon them. And we with a compleat, upright, and good intention endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring alike the performance of both, do thank God, that he hath ſo bleſſed our rule, love, and care to and for the good of our ſubjects, that they have requited the ſame with manifeſt expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of their reall love and ready obedience, tending both to their and our welfare, ſtrength and conſervation. And in reſpect of the Engliſh Nation, have ever, not only with all unfainedneſs and holineſs on our parts maintained all friendſhip and good correſpondency, which of old uſed to be obſerved between them and us: but moreover the ſaid Engliſh Nation now of late be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſturbed within her own bowells, and rent in factions, and the people highly exaſperated one againſt the other, we have not only with ſorrow and ſadneſſe of heart beheld the ſame, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115319:3"/>
abſtained from all partiall actions, whereby we might incur the juſt diſpleaſure or diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffaction of either ſide: and moreover, as much as poſſibly we could, prevented and ſtopped all ſuccour from us to either of them, whereby the fire which was kindled might be fomented, the breach made larger, and the cure more difficult and perillous; but alſo when the aforeſaid deſtractions had in ſome parts of their Country occaſioned waſt, deſolation, poverty, want of food; and we, by both Houſes of Parliament at that time being, were earneſtly intreated to admit of a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like collection in our Churches for the conſolation and ſuſtenance of many impoveriſhed and needy people in the ſaid parts: the repreſentation of the ſaid calamities did ſo work upon our hearts and the hearts of our good ſubjects with tender pity and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an compaſſion, that upon the ſaid intreaty a conſiderable ſum of money, to the value of certain Tonnes of gold, was gathered in, and to the ſaid end exported out of this Country, inſomuch that the ſaid Houſes of Parliament did cauſe their Letters of Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving to be diſpatched unto us, and to be exhibited and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the mouth of their publique Miniſter, with externall demonſtrations of great affection. With all which, finding our ſelfs not fully ſatisfied, but being deeply touched with a longing zeale and fervent deſire, to ſee an end put to all theſe ſaid miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, and thence ariſing troubles, and to have a true, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and innerly reconciliation made between theſe two ſo much each againſt the other incenſed and exaſperated parties; truſting we had given ſuch manifeſt demonſtrations of our true intentions herein, that we had hoped we might prove acceptable, and thereby alſo fitting inſtruments to help the furtherance of ſo good and great a work: to that purpoſe did undertake to make a tryall thereof, by ſending to the King and both Houſes of Parliament an Embaſſage Extraordinary impoſed upon the Lords <hi>William Boreel</hi> and <hi>Johan van Rheede, Lord of Renſwoude, &amp;c.</hi> But God Almighty in his incomprehenſible judgement not ſeeing good to put an end to the ſaid diſtractions by appeaſing the ſame, but by other means having ſetled the ſtate of that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment upon another ground then formerly it was maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by; and the ſaid Government offering unto us a treaty of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Union and neerer Alliance; we believing the ſame was
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115319:3"/>
preſented in all ſincerity and uprightneſs, and conſidering that thereby might be obtained ſecurity of Navigation and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, not only for us, but alſo for all Trading Kingdomes and Countries, eſpecially the Neighbouring, which otherwiſe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of divers common Intereſts, through miſunderſtandings ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing between us and the ſaid Government, inevitably would be diſturbed; we have not only ſhewed our ſelfs moſt willing and ready to accept of the ſaid motion, but the ſaid Government to that purpoſe having ſent over unto us the Lords, <hi>Oliver S. John,</hi> and <hi>Walter Strickland</hi> their Embaſſadors Extraordinary: we have alſo endeavoured in all manner to comply with them, and to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitate the means to bring the ſaid treaty to a happy concluſion, as far as the conſtitution of our preſent Government was able to ſuffer. So that the ſaid Lords Embaſſadors being entred into conference with our Lords the Committee ordained out of the midſt of us to that purpoſe; and having made unto them a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and unlimited Propoſition, after that we had made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt unto them our ſincere inclination and true love to Peace and Unity, they were in our behalf requeſted, that the ſaid generall Propoſition by a neerer Expoſition might be opened might be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened and diſtinguiſhed in cleare and near points, that thereby upon ſure and firm grounds things might be brought to a good concluſion; and although ſeverall well-grounded reaſons were alledged, and by ſeverall contra-propoſitions good way was made for an agreement: Nevertheleſſe at that time we could ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance nothing, but that the ſaid Lords Embaſſadors, when a ſhort time was expired after their firſt audience, the ſubſtance it ſelfe not once yet being touched, gave countenance that they were to depart. But through ſundry perſwaſions, at laſt admitting of a willingneſs to prolong their time of ſtaying, and having ſince exhibited neerer Propoſitions, we have with all ſpeed approved our ſelfs ſo, that the ſaid Lords Embaſſadors, upon the ſaid neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Propoſitions (which themſelfs declared to be of greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, and of ſuch conſequence, that when once we ſhould come to be of one reſolution concerning the ſame, there would be little difficulty in the other) have received from us ſuch refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that in the ſubſtance there remained no difference, or if any, but very ſmall; and we of our parts moreover revealed all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115319:4"/>
that we found conducing further to the good of both Nations, that might be agreed upon with maintenance of the alliances we have with other Kings, Republiques, Princes and States, and ſo all that was needfull for the conſummating of the ſaid trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; whereunto expecting the neerer Declaration of the ſaid Lords Embaſſadors, they declined the ſame by their ſuddain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, intimating, that the time granted unto them for their ſtaying was expired, and conſequently that they could not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly proceed to an anſwer unto that which was propounded by us, to the end aforeſaid. And although the ſaid manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding might afford matter of ſeverall ſuſpitions, concerning the intention of the ſaid Government, in relation to the ſaid treaty: becauſe the intercurrence of a ſhort time, which had made no alteration in the cauſe it ſelfe, ought not to have alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the good inteutions, and conſequently ought not to have made any ſuch interruption in the progreſs of the treaty: we notwithſtanding on our parts (preferring the dignity and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſſe of the cauſe it ſelf before all outward ceremonies, and conſidering the proteſtation made by their ſaid Lords Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors at their departure from hence, of the ſincere inclination of the ſaid Government towards peace, and of their confidence, that although their endeavours had not been ſo ſucceſſive, as to attain to a happy period, the ſame notwithſtanding might not prove unfruitfull, when time ſhould come, that we with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra-viſit ſhould pleaſe to reſort unto them) have not omitted to decree a conſiderable Embaſſage to the ſaid Government, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly in December laſt year ſent thither the Lords <hi>Jacob Cats, Gerard Schaep,</hi> and <hi>Paulus van de Par,</hi> our Embaſſadors Extraordinary, with full power and inſtructions for a Treaty. Although ſince the departure from hence of the ſaid Lords S. <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Strickland,</hi> by a certain diſcourteous and unneighbourly Act, publiſhed by the ſaid Government, whereby the uſuall liberty of Trade was manifeſtly reſtrained, the good correſdondency be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween both Nations (whereby true friendſhip and fidelity were wont beſt to increaſe and be confirmed) was in that part evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently cut off, and ſeverall of our Ships ſurpriſed, all which gave more and more ſuſpitions, that the intentions of the ſaid Government was no way anſwerable to our unfained open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartedneſs,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115319:4"/>
which afterward did moſt evidently appeare to be ſo. For after that our ſaid Embaſſadors Extraordinary were ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived in England, and there had made an earneſt and upright De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, of our ſincere affection towards the conſummating of the afore-mentioned inchoated treaty, with ſerious Requeſts, that the ſame might ſpeedily and happily be brought to a perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and to that end all things might ſtand in the ſame poſture, wherein they were left at that time, when the ſaid Lords <hi>St. Iohn</hi> and <hi>Strickland</hi> departed from us; at leaſt till the event of that Treaty might be known: and to that purpoſe the ſaid Act (by which the life and being of the ſaid Treaty would be infringed) might be repealed, or at leaſt the execution thereof ſuſpended, and the ſurpriſed Ships and goods reſtored: The ſame hath not only not been taken into conſideration by the ſaid Government, as was fitting it ſhould according to reaſon and equity; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily (during the ſaid Treaty for the renewing and confirming of old Covenants and Amity, and of the entrance into neerer confederacy and compliance of Love and Union) the ſaid Act was put in Execution, and moreover under ſeverall unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able pretenſes, as partly with Letters of Mart, granted by the ſaid Government without cauſe (in reſpect we never denied or delaid Juſtice to any of their offended ſubjects, being therefore contrary to the Laws and practiſes of all civilized Governments, and to all former Covenancs erected betwixt both Nations) partly with Commiſſions given againſt the French, the Ships of our ſaid Subjects have been aſſaulted at Sea, entered, ſurpriſed, and brought up into their Havens in a moſt hoſtile manner, the Goods plundered, the Maſters and Mariners roughly uſed, as well by their publike Miniſters, as by thoſe which were inabled by the ſaid Letters or Commiſſions, and thereby given occaſion to all ſorts of Robbers under the ſame pretences, to exerciſe their pira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, not giving regard to the conſtant ſolicitings of our ſaid Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors to the ſaid Government, that they would pleaſe to cauſe ſuch actions to ceaſe; much leſſe making reſtitution to our good Subjects of their ſurpriſed and plundered ſhips and goods. And although by theſe unneighbourly actions we had juſt cauſe given us to manifeſt our reſent, and by retortion to ſeek repaira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the dammages, which our Subjects ſuſteined, from and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115319:5"/>
upon the ſhips and goods of the Subjects of that Government, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> being thereunto highly provoked through an unſufferable out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage: Nevertheleſſe hoping the ſaid Government would once give place to reaſon, and that by way of treaty, according to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and equity, all differences might be compoſed; we have abſteined from all manner of fact; yea though earneſtly intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, have refuſed to give our Letters of Mart or Commiſſions to our wronged Subjects for reaſons afore-mentioned; and of our ſide through our Embaſſadors Extra-ordinary with all earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſought the accompliſhing of the ſaid treaty in generall, and of the afore-mentioned ſurpriſed ſhips and goods in particular: and on the other ſide to prevent all piracy and robbery for the future, and to free our Subjects from further loſſes, and the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall commerce from a totall ruine and ſpoile; we reſolved to ſet out at ſea a conſiderable fleet of ſhips, and to prevent jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and that the ſaid Government might not miſ-apprehend of this our doing (as we did like wiſe to other our friends and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring countries) by our Embaſſadors extra-ordinary we gave notice unto them in all ſincerity of this our reſolution, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and upright manifeſtations, that the ſaid ſhips ſhould not at the leaſt be imployed to inflict any hurt upon our friends and confederates, and namely alſo not upon the Subjects of their Government: but that we were of a ſetled reſolution to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain all good compliance and friendſhip with them in ſincerity, as was becoming two ſuch neighbouring Nations. And although we expected that this notice given, ought alſo to have been accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of by them, as a token of our unfainedneſſe, eſpecially becauſe the ſaid Government a little time before had manifeſted their diſtaſte, that a ſmall number of our ſhips, not giving them time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly notice aforehand, had ſhewed themſelfs neare unto ſome Iſlands, which then our ſhips knew not to be under their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: Notwithſtanding we obſerved, that the ſaid Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment daily aiming at nothing more, then to gather pretences, whereby to give a colour to the execution of their long threatened deſignes, have alſo looked upon the ſaid notificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the ſame glance: inſomuch that our Embaſſadors were neceſſitated in our behalf to bring more proofs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to make the truth thereof more apparent unto them.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115319:5"/>
And in the meane time, that the ſaid treaty was ſeriouſly followed by our ſaid Embaſſadors, who endeavoured to bring the ſame into ſuch a poſture, that the ſaid Government ſhould be induced to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare themſelves, and no longer to conceale their ſecret deſignes, tending to the deſtruction of our commerce, and the diſabling of the ſtrength of our ſtate, under ſeeming pretenſes of friendſhip, and feeding us with the hopes and appearances of a treaty: as we have moſt evident proofs of this their doing: Our Lieutenant Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall <hi>Tromp,</hi> whom we made Generall of our ſaid Navy, was by them encountred with a full broad ſide in an hoſtile manner, and ſeverall of the men of his ſhip miſerably wounded, becauſe he did not ſtrike the flagge according to their fancy, though nevertheleſſe according to divers unanimous Declarations and evidences taken of neutrall and unpartiall men, he was buſie with haling in of his Mars-ſayle, and cauſing of his boat to be haled on, whereby to ſend one of his Officers aboard of the Admirall of the ſaid Government to congratulate him with all due reſpects; by which encounter our ſaid Lieutenant Admirall, and the reſt of the ſhips under his commande, were neceſſitated to defend themſelves, and did moderate their defence ſo irreprehenſibly, in regard of the Engliſh Navy, that whereas ours were farre ſtronger in number of ſhips, and able to have wholly ruinated their invaders, they refrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves and reſted ſatisfied with their onely defence. Which diſcretion notwithſtanding by the adverſe party was ſo little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected, that, comming up with a ſecond Eſquadron of ſhips, they did likewiſe in their former hoſtile manner aſſault the hindermoſt of our ſhips, which were ſeperated from the body of our fleete, overcame two of them, and tooke one away. And to make this encounter ſerve them for a pretenſe, to break the aforeſaid treaty, they gave out and publiſhed amongſt their people, and have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to make the whole world beleeve, that the firſt aſſault in the ſaid encounter was made by our ſide, and thence pretend to be wronged and affronted in the higheſt degree, and ſet themſelves in a poſture of open warre againſt us, before they once made the leaſt complaint thereof unto us, much leſſe damanding reparation for the ſaid treſpaſſe, which they pretend to be committed, which reaſon and reſpect to the treaty in hand, if ever their intention to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſame had been reall, might have perſwaded them. On the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115319:6"/>
contrary we on our ſides endeavouring with true and upright hearts and mindes to reduce into a due Frame and Order, what might be diſplaced and out of order; our aforeſaid Embaſſadors Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, no ſooner had received intelligence of the ſaid accident, but with moſt ſeriouſneſſe proteſted and declared before the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of State of the ſaid Government, that if things had beene acted, as they related the ſame, that we were wholly ignorant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to be done quite contrary to our exprrſſe order, which they confirmed by exhibiting the originall letter written unto them by the aforeſaid our Admiral concerning the ſaid ſubject, comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a perfect relation of the commiſſion we gave him, and ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly atteſting of our intimate deſires, and hearty inclinations to have and maintaine peace and unity with the ſaid Government by a firme alliance, and indiſſoluble amity: and with great zeale and earneſt inſtances beſeeched them, that there might a nearer ſearch be made into the truth of paſſages befallen in the ſaid encounter, and thereupon communicated unto them the evidences taken there, to be ſent over unto us: and deſired that in the meane time the treaty, which they ſuppoſed was brought ſo far, that in a ſhort time it might receive its happy period, might not be retarded by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected caſualty, beyond and againſt will, ſurely of us, through in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderateneſſe and raſhneſſe of one of the two parties officers, who were to give accompt of their actions, and that the ſame might not put the cauſe in a farther diſtance. And although this propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition was of great conſequence &amp; higheſt importance for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good of both nations, the ſaid government notwithſtanding in a long time have not dained our Embaſſadors, nor us, in whoſe behalfe the ſame was propounded, with their anſwer: being how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever by our ſpeciall command a ſecond time put in minde thereof by our ſaid Embaſſadors, who again delivered over the ſaid renewed propoſition, and afterwards reiterated it once more, with further confirmations of our upright intention &amp; hearty diſpleaſure againſt the ſaid unexpected and unhappy encouneer of the ſaid Fleets. Yea on the contrary laid hold upon all Ships of traffick and men of warre, which they could light on at Sea, belonging to theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, taking or ſinking ſome with violence, miſleading others un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhew, and ſending them up into their harbours, alſo plundring and miſuſing the Seamen and Souldiers, and impriſoning divers, as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115319:6"/>
if we were in open warres with each other, without a forgoing pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick deniall of their Friendſhip towards us, which hath occaſioned the loſſe of much innocent blood, and the utter undoing of ſeverall of our ſubjects in their eſtates. All which extreame provocations we have with patience undergone to juſtifie before the world our peaceable mindes, and the uprightneſſe and lawfulneſſe of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, as ſhewing that nothing is more deare unto us then the accompliſhment, preſervation and augmentation of good union, true confidence, faithfulneſſe and amity with our neighbours; and contrarywiſe nothing more deteſtable then the horrible fruits of a conſuming war, and direfull waſting of innocent Chriſtian blood: And in conſideration thereof beſides our aforeſaid three Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors which we had ſent to the aforeſaid Government for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and eſtabliſhing of the aboveſaid alliance, we have moreover reſolved upon a ſecond Embaſſage Extraordinary to be ſent to the ſaid Government, and therefore diſpatched unto them the Lord <hi>Adrian Pauw,</hi> Lord of Heemſtede, our Penſionary Counſellor of Holland and Weſtfricſland, eſpecially upon the ſubject of the ſaid late encounter and its influences, and with more ſerious expreſſions of our upright meaning and deſire to pacifie the matter. And the ſaid Government having in the meane time given out their anſwer to the aforeſaid propoſition and iterative repreſentation of the ſame made unto them by our former Embaſſadors, in which anſwer having bended their affections to imbrace a bad &amp; ſiniſter impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which they wittily fitted and framed for a colour to their unjuſt and ungodly deſignes, as if we had ſet out and managed our ſaid fleete, for to make war againſt them, and to deſtroy their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, or to ſhew other actions of hoſtility, violence or oppreſſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their ſubjects, without any regard to all former ſerious atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations and proteſtations to the contrary, have declared, that they found themſelves obliged to endeavour, with Gods aſſiſtance, as they ſhall have opportunity, to ſeeke repairation of the wrongs (as they ſay) already ſuffered and ſecurity that the like be not attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the future. And thereby ſhewed they had neither will nor inclination, to bring the matter to an accommodation, but were minded to goe on with matters of fact: The aboveſaid Lord of <hi>Heemſtede,</hi> both before the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> as likewiſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards before the Councell of State, with ſtrong and moſt cleare
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115319:7"/>
arguments diſproving the truth of the ſaid impreſſion, and calling God almighty, the ſearcher of all hearts, to witneſſe (he having perfect cognizance of all our affaires, becauſe, in regard of his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke charge, he had been preſent in all our conſultations, held both in our aſſemblies and in the aſſemblies of the States of Holland and Weſtfriſland) could and did holily proteſt and depoſe for the aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed truth, that never any deliberation was held, nor reſolution ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, much leſſe any power or commiſſion given directly or indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to give any the leaſt cauſe of offence to the ſaid Government, which is farre from an intention to of doing any injury to the ſaid Fleet, or any ſhips belonging to the ſame, but ſurely to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that they had order to manifeſt unto them all tokens of friendſhip and propitious affection: and once more from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of heart with all uprightneſſe proteſted, that the above ſaid Sea-fight, between the two Fleets happened without our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or order, to our great ſorrowfulneſſe and aſtoniſhment. And conſidering that nevertheleſſe the ſaid Government made another conſtruction of that ſad accident, then in truth it could afford, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ſaid conflict a rock of offence, and in their aforeſaid an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer ſpake of reparation of the wrongs and ſecurity for the future: the ſaid Lord of <hi>Heemſtede,</hi> according to inſtructions which he had received from us, confeſſing, that the ſaid rock of offence ought ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly to be removed, and all matter of diffidence taken away, and that he to that purpoſe and for the compaſſing thereof eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y was delegated and ſent over unto them, and to facillitate the meanes thereunto, he laboured diligently to have the ſaid inchoated and already far brought treaty in hand to goe on, and that further to the contentation of both States good inſtructions and orders might be framed and given to the ſaid Fleets on both ſides, which might be to them a rule for the future how to carry themſelves to each other, aſſuring them alſo, that we never was minded to call in queſtion the honour and reſpect, which in former times by this ſtate was wont to be deferred unto them: Requeſting further, that the ſaid Government in the meane time, whilſt they might be buſie in treating upon ſo good a matter, would once at length prudently give order, that all further ways of fact ſo long continued in reſpect of the aforementioned ſad accident, might ceaſe, whereas otherwiſe the evill was like to grow incurable. And after that in divers parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115319:7"/>
conferences held with the Lords of the Committee of the ſaid Councell of State, further declaring himſelfe in our behalfe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted and preſented, that a more narrow ſearch might be made into the evidences given in by both parties concerning the ſaid en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter by committees appointed on both ſides, and the ſame being examined and the naked truth found out, which ſide made the firſt atach, and thereby gave occaſion for the further diſorder and diſtemper thence ariſing; and if it ſhould appeare that our Admirall made the firſt attach, he not onely ſhould undergoe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, and his action be diſſallowed, but alſo, as having gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond his Commiſſion, be puniſhed according as the fact ſhould ſeeme to have deſerved: provided that the ſaid Government finding the caſe to be otherwiſe, that their Admirall by the evidences being found to have given the firſt hoſtile attach, he in like manner under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe puniſhment according as his act may have deſerved: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing his and our other Embaſſadours their former and ſo oft reiterated requeſt, that at leaſt whilſt this propoſition might be taken into conſideration, the former treaty in points of moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment might be inſiſted upon and furthered, the Ships and goods of our ſubjects, taken with violence, and brought up into their Harbours, reſtored, our Captaines, Ship-maſters and Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners relaxed and ſet free, and all further acts of hoſtility ceaſe. And although this propoſition was of ſuch nature, that no reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſoule, in which is but remaining any ſparke of inclination to peace, ought to reject the ſame: and that all this was illuſtrated with ſundry examples obſerved in like caſes betweene other nations, and was confirmed by divers ſolemne alledged treaties; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſaid Councell of State, being convicted in their hearts, that their declaration concerning what happened in and about the ſaid Sea-fight could not endure the light, &amp; therefore having no mind to ſearch into the truth (the concealing whereof ought to be counted ſacriledge to every man though in a particular caſe) they have ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely caſt off the ſaid examination, ſtopped the progreſſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the aforeſaid principall treaty, and moreover declared, that in the preſent conſtitution of things we might not expect from them, but that they would perſevere in the proſecution mentioned in their former anſwer given to the propoſitions of the aforeſaid Lords <hi>Cats, Schaep</hi> and <hi>van de Par,</hi> to ſuch end as was there exprſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115319:8"/>
Which laſt anſwer being tarter than the former, and more unreaſonable, full of injuſtice and violence in reſpect of our honeſt preſentation: and ſuch as gave cauſe ſufficient to us to deſiſt from all our friendly endeavours, eſpecially and the more becauſe they made no end of taking, robbing, plundering of ſhips and goods, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to our good ſubjects: nevertheleſſe the ſaid Lord of <hi>Heem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtede,</hi> for to ſhew our moſt conſtant inclination and earneſt deſire that all to the contentation of both ſides with friendſhip might be brought to a good and wiſhed concluſion, and to that end only ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting aſide all that otherwiſe in point of honour and reſpect might have been conſiderable, that the treaty might not wholy be broken off deſired, that in regard the endeavours on our part could not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the honour of an happy iſſue: the aforeſaid Government would pleaſe to think upon ſom other propoſitions for a peaceable agreement, truſting that once reaſon might finde place with them, and credit be given to our upright and unfeined proteſtations, and the ſweet influences of a deſire to peace conſume the turbulent thoughts of war, and the good God laying open unto us ſuch means, the preſent and further threatned calamities might be averted. But the ſaid Government, as it appeared, miſ-uſing the ſuperfluity of our pliantnes to the fomentation of their pride and loftineſſe; our modeſty to kindle their heat towards deſtruction; our friendly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations for a ground to worke upon us and demand of us things, which by them with no ſhew of equity could be demanded, nor by us with honour and reputation granted, and amongſt the reſt were ſo unreaſonable as to require of us the charges and dammages, which they pretend to have been put upon, and to have ſuffered by reaſon of our afoerſaid extraordinary preparation of ſhips, to the value of ſuch a ſum as the ſame might be found to amount unto: &amp; the ſame being paid or ſecurity for it given to their content, then to have all acts of hoſtility to ceaſe; nor once minding, that our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid ſetting forth of ſhips was to no other end undertaken and effected, then is heretofore declared: and that as ſoon as the ſame was reſolved upon, and before it was put in action, we gave true and publike intelligence thereof to the ſaid Government; eſpecially ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the ſame fleet or any other ſhips belonging to theſe Provinces, there hath not been given to the ſaid Government, or to any of the ſubjects thereof, the leaſt token of diſaffection, much leſs of inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115319:8"/>
but cantrarily, that ours have beene aſſaulted by theirs, and ſome ſunk, others (amongſt which a great number of merchants ſhips rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lodened pertaining to theſe Countries) entred, overmaſtred, taken and carried up into their harbours, whereby we &amp; our ſubjects have ſuffered loſs of ſeverall millions of gilders: yea moreover during the ſaid treaty and conference have ſent their fleet to Sea, in all raſhneſs hurling on into the breach and diſſolution of all friendſhip and ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty between both nations, with an inſatiable luſt of making the ſame incurable, and therewith deſtroying and taking ſeverall of our ſhips more, enthralling our Government (which by God Almighty for many years hath been preſerved in a flouriſhing condition, and hath given reputation and awſulneſs with their friends and enemies) into a world of diſhonour and loſſes. All which intollerable and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full enterpriſes, and violent proceedings attempted and performed by the ſaid Government, do moſt perſpicuouſly and palpably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that their only deſign is, wholy to infringe our ſtrength at ſea, and to ruinate the commerce of theſe countries, and thereby to ſet up their long pretended Soveraignty and dominion over the Sea, which ſhortly they intend to exerciſe over us, and in time over all other nations, and if poſſibly they can, to make us and others their tributaries. And having with great patience and meekneſſe, but all in vaine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> improved all convenient meanes and rationall inductions, whereby to move the ſaid Government for the good and happineſſe of both their owne and our ſubjects, to ſtand off from the ſaid reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, that the riſen diſtempers might be aſwaged and compoſed, the ſhips and goods, with violence or otherwiſe taken and detained from our ſubjects, reſtored, the loſſes, which they have innocently ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteined made good; and by an upright and ſtrict binding treaty the old (but now of late times by that Government enforced and viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) friendſhip re-ſetled, and by mutual confiding offices more and more confirmed; but ſeeing no hope more of prevailing by ſuch means, <hi>We</hi> (according to the law of nature finding our ſelves obliged to defend our good ſubjects againſt all injury, oppreſſion and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, to cauſe them obtain reparation for the loſſes they have ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to re-eſtabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh the former due liberty of commerce, and to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the aforeſaid pernitious deſignes of the ſaid Government, which being drunken with ſucceſſes within their owne countries, ſeem to know no meaſure of their further unſatiable appetites a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115319:9"/>
as being hereunto by greateſt extremity impelled, with ripe, deliberation of councell, have at length reſolved and thought good, to uſe the power and meanes, which God and nature hath given us, and with our weapons by way of retorſion upon and againſt the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Government, and the ſubjects thereof, to endeavour the obtaining of that, which with reaſon could not be recovered of them; with a minde and intention not to lay downe the ſame, as long as the ſaid Government doth ſteere the courſe they now are in, and till the aforeſaid reſtitution of Ships and goods, and repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of inferred injuries be obtained. Being confident, that the whole world will approve of this our reſolution, forced from us with the utmoſt violence, and that Almighty God will bleſs our juſt cauſe; truſting alſo that all Kings, Republikes, Princes and States will take on this our manifeſt declaration for true, lawfull and requiſite, and with us will help to oppoſe and ſubdue all ſuch pernicious deſignes, and in this our conſtrained and no leſſe juſt and lawfull defence, ever and in all places, as occaſion ſhall offer, will lend their aſſiſtance to us and our good ſubjects. Even as we hereby ordeine all our ſaid ſubjects to the United Netherland Provinces, to oppoſe themſelves by way of retorſion, as aforeſaid, againſt all the violence and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, which more and more are threatned againſt them: and not to ſuffer themſelves further to be deluded by any whatſoever ſhew of friendſhip, or willingly to have recourſe to any place, where they muſt be uſed according to the appetite of the ſaid Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernmenti: And ſo both we and our ſubjects confiding in the juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our cauſe, ſhall hope for the bleſſing upon the meanes aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed for our lawfull defence from God Almighty.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Thus concluded and arreſted in the Gathering of the ſaid Potent Lords the States Generall, in the Hague, <date>the ſecond of <hi>Auguſt</hi> ſixteen hundreth and two and fifty.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Signed <hi>Johan van Reede tot Renſwoude</hi> vt. and underſtood: By ſpeciall command from the ſame: ſigned <hi>N. Ruyſch.</hi> And in the further ſpace bearing the impreſſion of the great Seale of the ſaid States Generall in red wax.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
